Guide to the University of Pittsburgh Division of Research in the Natural Sciences Office Files, 1930-1968 UA.90.4.1.2
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Foundations, General Information, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 110)
  Government University relationships, 1958; Danforth Foundation; National Academy of Sciences - Research associateships; Labor Foundation; Woodrow Wilson National fellowship foundation.
- General Correspondence, 1950-1958 (Box 12, Folder 111)
- Graduate School of Public and International Affairs, 1957 (Box 12, Folder 112)
- Graduate Study, 1956-1957 (Box 12, Folder 113)
  Report of Committee on Policies in Graduate Education, Association of Graduate Schools, October, 1957; Area of the Disciplines; Organization of Graduate study; Statement of policy regarding the awarding of advanced degrees to Professors and Associate Professors at the University of Pittsburgh; Appointments to Graduate faculty membership; Students; Policy on admission of students from abroad; Proposed procedure for handling applications for graduate student assistantships; Distribution of graduate students by major Department of graduate study, Spring 1956/1957; Degrees granted by major department, 1956/1957.
- Graduate Study - University of Pittsburgh Examination (U.P.E.), 1957 (Box 12, Folder 114)
- International Association of Universities, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 115)
- Mellon Institute, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 116)
  Old Mellon Institute building agreement with the University of Pittsburgh, 1958; Mellon Institute men teaching Chemistry and Mathematics at the University free of charge; "Pittsburgh's Mellon Institute" reprint.
- Middle States Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, 1950,1952 (Box 12, Folder 117)
  Correspondence about attending the evaluation, 1952; Standards for accreditation, November 1950.
- Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Fellowships and Courses, 1953-1957 (Box 12, Folder 118)
- Personnel Division - Leland P. Deck, 1957-1958 (Box 12, Folder 119)
  Salary plan for administrative and clerical positions, 1957; Classified clerical positions; The Disciplines; Employee scholarships; Graduate Student assistants, part-time faculty, 1958; Position classification; Salary adjustment and merit increases.
- Physical Plant - Director William G. Fisher, 1955-1958 (Box 12, Folder 120)
  Old Mellon Institute and alterations for Physics Department, 1958; George Hubbard Clapp Hall, 1958; Biophysics Department, 1957; Chemistry Department, 1957; Biological Sciences, 1957; Mathematics Department, 1957; Physics Department; General Physical plant; "Physical Education Plant for the University of Pittsburgh – Urban redevelopment area number 8" pamphlet, 1957; Building progress report and statements of construction accounts, January-November 1956; Physical plant operating procedure number 3, 1955.
- Natural Science Building No. 2, 1957-1958 (Box 12, Folder 121)
  Equipment price lists, 1958; Memos concerning the building and space.
- George Hubbard Clapp Hall Building Council, 1956-1957,1962 (Box 12, Folder 122)
- George Hubbard Clapp Hall, Memos, 1956-1958, 1962 (Box 13, Folder 123)
- George Hubbard Clapp Hall, 1948-1958 (Box 13, Folder 124)
  Building plan memos, pamphlets, and magazines.
- George Hubbard Clapp Hall, Correspondence, 1950-1953 (Box 13, Folder 125)
- George Hubbard Clapp Hall, Correspondence, 1953 (Box 14, Folder 126)
- George Hubbard Clapp Hall, Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 127)
- George Hubbard Clapp Hall, 1956-1957 (Box 14, Folder 128)
  Office Supply Orders; Bluerprint; Correspondence.
- Physics, Correspondence, 1952-1956 (Box 14, Folder 129)
- Psychology, Reports and Reprints, 1940-1958 (Box 14, Folder 130)
- Placement, 1957-1958 (Box 15, Folder 131)
- Police Department, 1957-1958 (Box 15, Folder 132)
- Planning and Development, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 133)
  National Institutes of Health asked for estimate of needs for a grant, 1958; Alumni Association fund goal for faculty salaries.
- Plant Virus Research Laboratory - Phipps Conservatory, 1948-1968 (Box 15, Folder 134)
  Sarah Mellon Scaife Foundation remodeled the Engineer's Building in Schenley Park to serve as a Plant Virus Research Laboratory, 1949; Engineer's Building leased by University for 20 years, 1948-1968.
- Public Relations, 1952-1958 (Box 15, Folder 135)
- Requisitions, 1946-1958 (Box 15, Folder 136)
- Research in the Natural Sciences, 1939-1943, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 137)
  Contracts listed; Progress reports on emergency research, 1943; Space needed for biochemistry; Record of facilities for research in specific fields, 1942; Minutes of the meeting of the Emergency Research Committee, 1942; Report of the Sub-committee on space requirements, March 1941; Nuclear research activities, 1948; Projects written up; Budget sheets, 1939/1940-1942/1943.
- Research in the Natural Sciences, 1946-1953 (Box 15, Folder 138)
  Statement on research in the Natural Sciences, 1953; Analysis of funds allocated in grants and fellowships, 1950-1952; Contracts in research, 1952/1953; Research grants and contracts, 1947; Report to the Chancellor, Research in the Natural sciences, 1946/1948; Annual report, 1945/1946; Proposed alterations in Alumni Hall, 1946.
- Research in the Natural Sciences, 1944,1953-1955 (Box 15, Folder 139)
  History of the Department which began in 1944; Memo to Dr. Nutting on the activities of the Division, 1955; Annual reports of each department, 1955/1956; Annual report, 1953/1955; Issues for consideration in relation to University Research policy, 1954; Proposal to the Buhl Foundation for additional facilities; Government Institutional Research policy, 1953.
- Science Conferences, 1957-1958 (Box 16, Folder 140)
- Security Information, Department of Defense, 1951-1957 (Box 16, Folder 141)
  Clearance papers, 1951-1957; Report of Proceedings, Industry-Navy research and development conference, 1957.
- Students, Correspondence, 1951-1957 (Box 16, Folder 142)
- Teacher Education Project (Box 16, Folder 143)
  Proposal for a summer institute for high school teachers of chemistry and physics; Proposed research project in teacher education: Dr. Hutson's suggestion for improvement.
- Temple University, Foundation Grants for Experiments in Teacher Education, 1954 (Box 16, Folder 144)
- "This Week", 1957-1958 (Box 16, Folder 145)
  Issues publishing the items concerning faculty in the Natural Sciences, 1957-1958.
- University Senate Committees, 1957-1958 (Box 16, Folder 146)
  Education Policies Committee regarding leaves of absence for faculty members and emeritus status; Report of tenure and academic freedom committee, 1958; Budget policies committee report, 1957; Library and University Publications Committee; Committee on Sabbatical leaves, 1956; Proposed organization of Graduate study.
- University Visitors, 1954-1957 (Box 16, Folder 147)
  Dr. Glenn Olds: Honorable Austen H. Albu; Members of the General Assembly of Pennsylvania; Leo A. DeSousa; Engineer Jaime Orpinas Perello; Sir Lawrence Bragg; Dr. J. W. Mitchell.
- Sabbatical Leaves, 1957-1958 (Box 16, Folder 148)
- Guiding Principles for Appointments, 1956 (Box 16, Folder 149)
- University of Pittsburgh "Polio Report," No. 1-2, 4-8, 1957 (Box 16, Folder 150)
- "Pechan Bill" or Pennsylvania Loyalty Act, 1951 (Box 16, Folder 151)
  Guide to subversive organizations and publications, May 14. 1951; "What about communism?," Cast of Temple University; Statement on Roy Harris; Academic freedom and civic responsibility.
- Lowy, Alexander - Memorial Room, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 152)
- Patents, 1942-1950 (Box 17, Folder 153)
- Higher Education, National Affairs, 1954,1957 (Box 17, Folder 154)
- Educational Exchange, Department of State, 1953 (Box 17, Folder 155)
- U.S. Department of Agriculture, Special School Milk Program, 1954 (Box 17, Folder 156)
- U.S. Public Health, 1955 (Box 17, Folder 157)
  Pamphlets listing research grants; Memorandum for applicants, 1955.
- Tuition fee allowance, 1955-1957 (Box 17, Folder 158)
- U.S. Public Health, Grants, 1956-1959 (Box 17, Folder 159)
- Atomic Energy Commission - Correlation of Radiation Effects with Physical and Chemical Changes in Viruses (Box 17, Folder 160)
- Aluminum Company of America (ALCOA), 1938 (Box 18, Folder 161)
- Gulf Company, Graduate Work for Employees, 1932-1933 (Box 18, Folder 162)
- Westinghouse Co., Graduate Program, 1933-1934 (Box 18, Folder 163)
- Division of Research in the Natural Sciences, Reports, 1930-1931 (Box 18, Folder 164)
  Annual report, 1930/1931; Graduate School reports.
- Graduate School, Annual Report, 1931-1934 (Box 18, Folder 165)
- Graduate School, Annual Report, 1935-1936 (Box 18, Folder 166)
- Graduate School, Annual Report, 1936-1937 (Box 18, Folder 167)
- Graduate School, Annual Report, 1938-1939 (Box 18, Folder 168)
- Allegheny Observatory, 1956 (Box 18, Folder 169)
  Correspondence concerning the Keeler telescope, 1955: Amateur Astronomer's Institute, 1956.
- Biology, Appointments, 1956 (Box 18, Folder 170)
- Biophysics, Recommendations, 1956 (Box 18, Folder 171)
- Chemistry, Recommendations (Box 18, Folder 172)
- Chemistry, Finances, 1958-1959 (Box 18, Folder 173)
- Electron Microscope Lab, 1944-1945, 1954 (Box 18, Folder 174)
  Income received from the Lab, 1954; Proposal for electron microscope studies; Reports of visits to Eastern Electron Microscope labs; New microscopes manufactured by Radio Corporation of America, 1944; Article prepared for "Pitt," March 29, 1945; "Magnification calibration of the electron microscopes using thin plastic films cast on diffraction gratings" thesis by George Mechlin, 1944; "Thin section methods for the electron microscopic examination of curet polymers" paper by H. C. O'Brien, Jr.
- The College, 1953-1955 (Box 18, Folder 175)
  Correspondence concerning expenditures and staff, 1953-1955.
- Mathematics, 1956-1957 (Box 18, Folder 176)
  Exchange visitor program - Dr. Enrico Bompiani, 1956; Quantitative estimates for the Spring semester 1956/1957.
- Medicine, School of - Proposal to Commonwealth Fund, 1957 (Box 18, Folder 177)
- Microanalytical Laboratory, 1945-1947 (Box 18, Folder 178)
  Correspondence; Cost-estimate of equipment, 1945; Services rendered, 1947; Carrier-Weathermaker for Laboratory, 1947.
- Physics, Personnel and Budget, 1956 (Box 18, Folder 179)
- Psychology, Recommendations, 1956-1957 (Box 18, Folder 180)
- Registration, 1891-1933 (Box 18, Folder 181)
  Degrees granted, 1891-1931; Doctorates conferred in sciences, 1932/1933; Deduction on tuition for faculty of other colleges.
- Spectroscopy Laboratory, 1945-1951 (Box 19, Folder 182)
  Cooperation with the American Steel & Wire Company, 1951; Correspondence of Mary E. Warga, 1948; Contract with St. Joseph Lead Company; Program of Ninth Pittsburgh Conference on Applied Spectroscopy; Visit of Mademoiselle Yvette Cauchois to give a Seminar, 1950; Sixth Pittsburgh Conference on applied spectroscopy, 1945.
- Tropical Testing Laboratory, 1944-1957 (Box 19, Folder 183)
  Correspondence with commercial companies who will use the Laboratory, Dr. Peter Gray in charge of the research; Recommendations for appointments, 1945.
- Budget, 1931,1936,1957 (Box 19, Folder 184)
  Recommendations and expenses; Buhl Foundation, 1931, 1936.
- Benoy, Marjorie, 1945-1948 (Box 19, Folder 185)
- Bragg, Sir Lawrence, 1948-1949 (Box 19, Folder 186)
  Presentation posters; Guest lists.
- Cox, Gerald J., 1953 (Box 19, Folder 187)
  General Correspondence; Science Journals.
- Crawford, Stanton C. - Dean of Faculty, 1958-1964 (Box 19, Folder 188)
- Frank, Henry S. - Chemistry, 1951-1956 (Box 19, Folder 189)
- Geise, John - Student Affairs, 1945-1959 (Box 19, Folder 190)
- Jones, Putnam F. - Dean of Graduate Faculty, 1957 (Box 19, Folder 191)
- Kurtzman, David H. - Chancellor, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 192)
- Lipiec, Tadeusz, 1947-1948 (Box 19, Folder 193)
- Litchfield, Edward H. - Chancellor, 1958-1968 (Box 19, Folder 194)
- Longenecker, Herbert E. - Dean of Research in Natural Sciences, 1960-1962 (Box 19, Folder 195)
  Correspondence between the University of Pittsburgh and Tulane; Science Journal.
- Peake, Charles H. - Assistant Chancellor for Student Affairs, 1956-1958, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 196)
- Rankin, Alan C. - Executive Assistant to the Chancellor, 1957 (Box 19, Folder 197)
- Van Dusen, A.C. - Vice Chancellor for Professional Schools, 1956-1959 (Box 19, Folder 198)
- Lauffer, Max - Head of Biophysics, 1947-1957 (Box 19, Folder 199)
  Correspondence with Thomas E. Cartswright, Eugene Perkins, and Andrew Petrie; Bituminous Coal Research Inc., 1957; Alcoa Foundation fellowship, 1956; Philip Broughton (A.W. Mellon Charitable Trust) about proposal for scientific equipment; Campbell Moses about application for American Cancer Society grant.
- Research in the Natural Sciences - Reports to the Buhl Foundation, 1936-1946 (Box 20, Volume 1)
- Research in the Natural Sciences - Reports to the Buhl Foundation, 1946-1949 (Box 20, Volume 2)
- Research in the Natural Sciences - Reports to the Buhl Foundation, April 1949 (Box 20, Volume 3)